[SPEAKER_01]: So, a few questions about consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is viññāṇa, consciousness, does that equal awareness?
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: The answer is no.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can be... you can choose to be aware and you can choose... well, you could be unaware or distracted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, you are conscious.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, awareness is only possible because you're already conscious.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if a person starts to look at their experience, and they haven't come across Buddhism or any other spiritual teaching, and they say, what is happening here?
[SPEAKER_01]: Here is a...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm feeling something.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm perceiving things, you know, visual things, sounds, smells, tastes, touches.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm having thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have desires, intentions, wishes, and I have a... so that's...
[SPEAKER_01]: I have a body, you know, to some extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: They see that and understand that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I'm aware of my situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm aware of these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know it and I can pay attention here and there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how would... they wouldn't necessarily come up with this idea of consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you see that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can be aware of all these components.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot be aware of your consciousness directly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot be conscious of your consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how would you know that it even is such a thing?
[SPEAKER_00]: The purification that the suttas would be describing, purification of your intention, purification of greed, aversion, delusion, removal of those things from
[SPEAKER_00]: Your assumptions, from your intentions, from your choices, that's what develops your awareness, your self-awareness, self-awareness of your situation and dispassion that comes from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why, through the practicing of purification of dispassion, consciousness will be fully understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: How to say it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Consciousness is to be fully understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't understand it by sort of making an object of it in your thinking, because obviously that won't be the consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Consciousness is kind... it's on the level where the... where the form is, where the perceptions are, like on their own, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not something you do.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the fact that you... as I said, the fact that you can be aware, that you can intend this or that, means your conscious form is already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And any attempt to access, or get to, or see directly that consciousness part of that experience, of the five aggregates of the experience as a whole, you're not going to be seeing the consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why only through fully developing this passion towards form, towards feelings, towards perceptions, towards intentions, what you're left with,
[SPEAKER_00]: The passion will be removed from that as well, and that will be the full understanding of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's another thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you try to understand consciousness, or try to understand your feelings, or try to understand your intentions, or try to understand the form, it can only be done on the basis of inseparable five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot be thinking just the consciousness, or thinking just the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whenever you single one of those, all five, the experience as a whole, is already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, person needs to recognize that, because obviously, your views and assumptions can be kind of implying and hoping that you could figure out or access or see or perceive the pure consciousness of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why any view that revolves around the ideas of pure consciousness is a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you're gonna have, doesn't matter how subtle, how coarse, how unfamiliar, how familiar, how big or small, expensive or shrunk experience you might have, it's the experience of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: How fleeting, how slow, it's the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all you can have.
[SPEAKER_00]: And any single aspect of the five aggregates that you pick up with your attention, with your assumptions, it's the five aggregates again.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's five aggregates within the five aggregates within the five aggregates within the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter what direction you go.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, first and foremost, you have to stop thinking about consciousness as some sort of entity that exists there, to which things appear.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, those are your images.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those are your mental images, your mental thoughts, the dhammas, the phenomena that appear because you're already conscious, because your form is there, not bereft of consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's the only way, as I should say, to fully understand the consciousness is to become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, the only way to fully understand the consciousness is to be completely free from passion, completely free from ill-will, completely overcome the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything else is going to come short.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going to be carrying one assumption or the other, one gratuitous standpoint or the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how far can we go with our understanding, without being arahants, then?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even though we kind of come short?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you go as far as you practice the dispassion rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't go as far through thinking and pondering and proliferating about your ideas of consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's... to me, it all sounds like there is a living body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Say, if you take these terms, living body, dead body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Living body is the conscious body.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, to me, it sounds like that living part is what the... what we constitute as the... Well, colloquially, yes, you could say that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, again, you cannot step outside of the living part to see the full picture, which means there's going to be a gratuitous point placed at it that's limiting your perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's the the ultimate negative.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the ultimate negative.
[SPEAKER_00]: Think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the ultimate opposite end of the spectrum of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any standpoint in regard to the five aggregates that you take,
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you're going to be obscuring some part of that spectrum.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only way to have the entire spectrum unobscured is to completely, fully remove the slightest traces of appropriation and passion towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter whether it's the coarsest forms or the subtlest, most refined, most sublime, most abstract experiences.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the five aggregates and there is no part of it anywhere.
[SPEAKER_00]: that you are still holding on to.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, complete dispassion... That's why you don't really care if the consciousness is, eh... sublime, or if it... if your awareness is just, eh... awareness of light and mystical experiences, devoid of form.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's only relatively devoid of form.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because even the mental experiences are the experiences of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even the physical experiences are the experience of the consciousness spectrum of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even the coarsest physical experience of complete unawareness, consciousness is still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're inseparable.
[SPEAKER_00]: The five heaps are inseparable.
[SPEAKER_00]: And for as long as you're trying to find or think that understanding of the aggregates pertains to the content of a specific aggregates here and now, or now and then, or at some point, or experiencing specific types of feeling, developing specific types of perceptions in and of themselves, finding the real, pure, unpolluted consciousness is the way out.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it doesn't matter what mystical idea or scientific idea you might have, it's still the Five Aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only way to fully have the spectrum of the Five Aggregates that is uninterfered with, through gratuitous appropriation and so on, it's to remove passion, aversion and distraction in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the full understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the fully developed, so to speak, understanding of consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: I of the whole thing, of the five aggregates, there is nothing held back or obscured or hidden as a basis for your ownership, your sense of self, your conceit and everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what's what's nice about what you're saying there is that, because you hear full understanding of consciousness, you need to have that, you can be an arahant, so let me get the information about it, and then we figure it out, and then... Well, there's no problem in getting the information.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is what information I get.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and how far can you understand?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because people... because see, that's...
[SPEAKER_00]: You can be getting information, and you need to be getting information, and you need to... you need to even begin by getting the abstract information.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know, what the difference is, where to look for consciousness, just to give you some idea, to wrap your head around.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the bottom line is, it will have to boil down to, are you actually practicing, or just trying to figure it out on account of your fully corrupted five aggregates, and you're not doing anything about the corruptions?
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not doing anything about the limitations of your perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just on top of it, you're trying to piece everything together and get a perspective, ultimate perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you might start to practice, when everything is clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's never going to happen, because it's always going to be a limited standpoint.
[SPEAKER_00]: Something is always going to be left out, if you're coming from that standpoint of, I can see the spectrum, I can perceive the consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can step outside of the five aggregates and measure them, or basically imply a measure through thinking you're observing them impartially, objectively, as if failing to understand that you're objectively observing something is your subjective experience of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you cannot step outside of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: As you said so many times, you know, well, mentioned the suttas,
[SPEAKER_00]: Even like when people remember the previous lives and stuff, and when they sort of talk about it, it says, all they remember is the five aggregates, or one specific among them, among the group.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, in particular.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're completely enclosed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The whole saṃsara is the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: What maybe is more important, is to get that, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, obviously, we move all dispassion for the aggregates,
[SPEAKER_00]: No, develop this passion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry.
[SPEAKER_01]: Develop this passion for that good.
[SPEAKER_01]: But to know how enclosed you are, to get a feel for that, that understanding, rather than... Well, that's closer, that's closer to...
[SPEAKER_00]: Understanding consciousness, even if you don't think in terms of un-understanding consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that is... that is the... your direct experience, in a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is... that is the least proliferated perspective from what your experience actually is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the least corrupted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you haven't fully understood the five aggregates, through non-proliferation of greed, aversion, distraction, you are closer to seeing it how it is, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's... you are enclosed by the situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thinking...
[SPEAKER_01]: These things are not yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're undermined by all these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anicca, dukkha, anatta.
[SPEAKER_00]: And thus, unknowability of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anatta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just getting that feeling, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or that tone of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Getting that message.
[SPEAKER_01]: Perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Getting that perspective across.
[SPEAKER_00]: Letting that perspective sink in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Rather than loads of information about it, but just... That you are approaching to that external point of view, as I often say.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: External, as in you think.
[SPEAKER_00]: that your thinking thinks outside of the five aggregates and trying to, as I said, piece it together from this external standpoint, failing to understand that your objective external standpoint is your subjective experience at that given time, which means there is no outside of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, while you're trying to figure out that consciousness and so on, you're kind of missing... you're not seeing from the actual perspective that you are... You are overlooking the domain where the practice is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why I say, like, just even keeping the precepts in the beginning, when you start, you start by keeping the precepts and purifying your coarse behavior, that's already doing the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's already preventing you from maintaining the behavior that carries a belief that you are outside of your senses, outside of your sense bases.
[SPEAKER_00]: The whole, like, attraction or aversion towards sense objects carries an implicit view
[SPEAKER_00]: that they're outside of my sense fields.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, the only way to experience sights is through your eyes seeing things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're perceiving your eyes seeing things.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not perceiving things, which is people do.
[SPEAKER_00]: They develop a view that I'm perceiving things and they forget about their eyes.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm tasting tastes, they forget about the the mouth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same with the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm perceiving sensations, they forget about the the the form, the matter, they're necessary for those perceptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: They overlook the sense bases.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all you can perceive is your body perceiving sensations.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you can hear is your ears hearing sounds.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't step outside of it and access the sounds directly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, that implication is carried.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because you actually, at some point, experienced things outside of your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's simply because you've been ignoring your sense bases, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: The body, the experience as a whole, here and now, you've been ignoring it for so long, that it's invisible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all you see is sense-objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, although it feels like I'm not... like a person might think, I'm not having an external view of myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't ever think like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you attracted to sense-objects?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you repelled by sense-objects?
[SPEAKER_00]: There's already an external view to your five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why you can philosophize and theorize all you want.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're not developing the virtue, in that right sense, of discerning the intention behind your actions, whether they're rooted in greed or non-greed, aversion or non-aversion, distraction or non-distraction, and cultivating that, you will never, then, come back on the level of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter how much you think about them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter what meditation experiences you might think you have.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all just within the five aggregates that are being overlooked.
[SPEAKER_00]: Within the six sense fields, sense bases, saḷāyatana, as I should say, they're completely invisible.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you see are sense objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even when people then perceive these sense objects, if they have kind of... if they're like in regard to my own body, for example, like sensations and stuff, they'll think, oh, these are the internal, these are the sense spaces.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, no, there again, it doesn't matter how internal your sensations might feel,
[SPEAKER_00]: They're perceived.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything that's perceived, it's on account of, as I said, existing sense bases that are overlooked.
[SPEAKER_00]: Underneath you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Invisible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Behind you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wherever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Invisible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, as I said, you... perception of these external counterparts, sense objects, sight, sound, smell, taste, sensations, those perceptions
[SPEAKER_00]: Through overlooking the internal basis, carry the assumption that that's outside of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even if you are perceiving things seemingly inside, the only reason it feels inside is because you're so far outside, that's in your assumption, that something that's less outside feels like inside.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you were to stop proliferating and feeding such behaviors through keeping the virtue, sense restraint, recognizing the responsibility behind your actions by body, speech and mind, by senses, by engaging with eyes and so on, you are bringing that line of what's internal, what's external, closer and closer and closer.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're seeing what's underneath.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, what's underneath becomes sort of
[SPEAKER_00]: Outlined.
[SPEAKER_01]: The behind becomes outlined.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, the sense bases, the counterparts, the other side of the spectrum.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's sort of becoming peripherally outlined.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're becoming aware of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's like developing the signs of the mind, the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's exactly the same, the same practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, that's the point I'm trying to, like, emphasize here, is that more often than not, a person will think, I don't have an external view.
[SPEAKER_00]: of my situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't carry that view.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that person, or whoever thinks that, needs to recognize that whether you think you're carrying the view or not, is not the measure of the view.
[SPEAKER_00]: What the measure is, is are you withdrawn from engaging with sense objects?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you withdrawn from acting out of your will?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you withdrawn from basically acting out of the five hindrances?
[SPEAKER_00]: If not, the only reason that you are still able to be affected by the five hindrances, still act out of greed, aversion, still act out of desires, is because you are still carrying an external view.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are still implying it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe not as much as before.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that external view being, just to be clear, that I am
[SPEAKER_01]: Outside.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that I can be.
[SPEAKER_00]: That at least part of my experience as a whole, of the five aggregates, is outside of this situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how it... That's how it feels.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, you could say that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when people practice watching these sensations, it feels like, oh, this is underneath of this experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: When people chase sensual objects out there in the world, it feels like they're outside of me over there, and I'm getting them through engaging with them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Failing to understand that even a mere possibility of going towards sense objects or going internally towards sensations, it's only possible because the sense fields, the saḷāyatana, is already there perceiving those things, perceiving those possibilities, enabling them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like they're already conscious.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's the conscious eye.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the only thing you can access is the conscious eye seeing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't access the thoughts either.
[SPEAKER_00]: No more that you can access sights.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, all of those things, sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, thoughts, or sight, sound, smell, taste, sensations, thoughts,
[SPEAKER_00]: You feel like they're external to your point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: They come from out there, I'm here.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's because there's still traces, or a lot, not just traces, of overlooking, seeing past the saḷāyatana, the six sense spheres, or the experience as a whole, or the five aggregates, whichever you describe it, in its right extent, in its entire spectrum, which includes that peripheral perception, because you can't look at it directly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for as long as there is... that perception is obscured through passion, aversion, distraction, there will be a degree of my point of view and everything else outside of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, there will be a degree of conceit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only arahant is truly, completely, thoroughly free from conceit, from the standpoint.